American Dialect Society Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
American Dialect Society Collection (a.k.a. The Hanley Collection; The Hanley Discs) 1931-1937
AFC 1984/011
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
28 boxes
24 linear feet
2,662 items (includes 893 recordings, 1,766 pages of manuscript materials, 2 graphic images, and 1 zip disk)
American Dialect Society
The American Dialect Society Collection contains field recordings of samples of regional American speech recorded between 1931-1937 for the Linguistic Atlas of New England (LANE) and the Dictonary of American Regional English (DARE), as well as related materials.
Scope and Content
The recordings in the American Dialect Society Collection consist of 893 audio discs (both originals and duplicates made from originals, which replaced absent originals). 466 duplicate discs were subsequently delivered to the Linguistic Archives at the University of Georgia, Athens; AFC retained the original discs from which these were recordings were made. The 891 discs kept by AFC include aluminum-based acetate discs, plastic discs, and 12 shellac pressings made from the original recordings. In some cases the original disc no longer exists and so the copy is the only source for the recording. In addition there is one tape copy of eighteen discs duplicated in 1972 by Frederic Cassidy at the University of Wisconsin.
Notes found on the disc sleeves were written by various individuals at different times. For example, they were written by interviewers and recordists when the recordings were made, shortly afterwards by researchers for the Linguistic Atlas of New England (LANE) project, and by researchers for the Dictionary of American Regional English (DARE). Some of these notes are marked with initials and dates; others are not. The card indexes, disc inventories, and transcripts were made by students under the direction of Miles Hanley, at the University of Wisconsin, during the 1940s. Because of Hanley's involvement, the collection is sometimes referred to as the "Hanley collection" or "the Hanley discs." Manuscript materials include documents produced during acquisition of the collection for demonstrations and presentation events (when the collection was formally given to the American Folklife Center), as well as material produced during the processing of the collection, and theses and articles related to the collection.
The American Dialect Society recordings were made between 1931 and 1937. In the early 1930s the Society began a long-term project to document the regional variation of American speech: The Linguistic Atlas of the United States and Canada. The first published result of the project, the Linguistic Atlas of New England (LANE), was published in three volumes between 1939 and 1944. Fieldworkers for the LANE project interviewed people in New England, and documented their speech with written phonetic transcriptions. Hans Kurath, director of the project and editor of LANE, suggested that fieldworkers make audio recordings of informants, in addition to the written transcriptions. Miles L. Hanley, associate director for LANE, developed a system for recording sound on aluminum discs, which used several automobile batteries as a power source. With this disc-cutting machine in the back of his car, he traveled through New England, making recordings of many LANE informants. Later, other fieldworkers followed Hanley's practice and used recording equipment to gather information from informants from various regions as well as New England.
Although the recordings the fieldworkers made were originally intended as supporting data for the Linguistic Atlas of New England, they were never used in this way. The recordings were used for teaching linguistics and for linguistic research. In the 1970s they provided material for the Dictionary of American Regional English, the first volume of which was published in 1985.
Persons recorded include informants, fieldworkers, and staff members for the LANE project. Many other individuals volunteered to have their speech documented by the dialectologists. Since the scholars were interested in a comprehensive dialect study of all of North America, they recorded speakers from all regions as opportunities arose. They recorded a few foreign-born speakers as well.
The recordings are predominantly interviews with native New Englanders, most of whom were elderly. As Margaret Waterman (see Appendix E ) has pointed out, these interviews provide a record of the speech, attitudes, and lives of people born in the 1840s and 50s. Other speakers include scholars and those whose dialect or language proved interesting to the collectors. The collectors also recorded their own voices, as they felt their dialects might influence the collection and analysis of the dialects of others. Among the famous persons recorded are actor/author Alistair Cooke, romance philologist Charles H. Grandgent, folklorists John Lomax and Alan Lomax, linguist Edward Sapir, and psychologist B.F. Skinner. Languages other than English on the recordings include French, German, Hebrew, Hidatsa, Passamaquoddy, and Zulu. The Gullah dialect is documented as well. Of particular interest are the fifteen interviews with former slaves, and the fifty-five recordings of storyteller Joshua Alley of Jonesport, Maine. Most of the recordings are spoken-word narratives or interviews, although there are a few recordings of songs. Informants were asked about their ancestry, so a good deal of genealogical information is preserved on the recordings. People also talked about their daily lives and their childhood memories, gave recipes, and described work and play activities. In addition, informants also shared personal-experience stories, legends, and traditional tales.
Five fieldworkers made sound recordings in connection with Linguistic Atlas of New England: Bernard Bloch, Marguerite Chapallaz, Miles L. Hanley, Archibald A. Hill, and Guy S. Lowman Jr. Other collectors contributed recordings, disc copies, and/or assisted LANE collectors in making recordings in their regions: For example, Walter C. Garwick contributed the recordings made at Berea College, John Lomax contributed two discs of black work songs, and Lorenzo Turner assisted in the making of the recordings of Gullah dialect.
Some discs were not marked with the collectors' initials, or the collectors' information on the discs is incomplete. For this reason, other LANE staff members who made recordings or participated in interviews did not receive credit on the discs or disc sleeves. Hans Kurath, in particular, almost certainly participated in many of the recording sessions. Many of the unsigned notes in or on the disc sleeves are thought to be his. Notes on discs and disc sleeves show that "J. D." made recordings with Marguerite Chapallaz. This was Jane E. Daddow, a student of Hans Kurath. Contributing to the confusion as to the identity of the collectors is that the recordist and the interviewer were not always the same person. In addition to the researchers already mentioned, Robert L. Stone served as recordist for many interviews. Notes on the discs and disc jackets attribute some recordings to "Caffee" and "A. R. M.," who were probably recordists. The full names of these individuals are not given in the collection materials. See Appendix D for a detailed list of these and other abbreviations in the collection.
The Selected Bibliography (see Appendix E ) includes articles and other publications regarding the genesis and work of the American Dialect Society, including DARE and LANE.
Administrative History
The American Dialect Society was founded in 1889 for the study of the English language in North America, and other languages and their dialects of other languages as they relate to North American English. The Society produces the journal American Speech, and related monographs, holds annual and regional meetings, and sponsors the Dictionary of American Regional English. From 1889-1939, it published the journal Dialect Notes. The Society's web site is located at http://www.americandialect.org.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ashton, Sally; Bloch, Bernard, 1907-1965; Boyd, Phoebe; Brooks, Sarah Ashton; Chapallaz, Marguerite; Cooke, Alistair, 1908-2004; Grandgent, C. H. (Charles Hall), 1862-1939; Hanley, Miles L.; Hill, Archibald A., 1902-1992; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002; Lomax, John A. (John Avery), 1867-1948; Lowman, Guy Sumner, 1909-1941; Polite, Samuel; Quall, Susan A.; Quarterman, Wallace; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939; Skinner, B. F. (Burrhus Frederic), 1904-1990; Thompson, Susanna Rebecca Wright; Turner, Lorenzo Dow
Organizations
American Dialect Society
Subjects
English language--Dialects--Canada.; English language--Dialects--Maritime Provinces.; English language--Dialects--New England.; English language--Dialects--Sea Islands.; English language--Dialects--United States.; English language--Provincialisms--North America.; Farm life--United States.; Fiddle tunes--New England.; Fishing--New England.; Folk songs, English--New England.; Fowling--United States.; Freedmen--United States--Interviews.; Hidatsa Indians.; Hunting--United States.; Linguistics--Research--North America.; Passamaquoddy Indians.; Sea Islands Creole dialect.; Slave narratives--Southern States.; Slavery--Southern States--Anecdotes.; Songs, Zulu.; Storytelling--United States.; Tales--United States.; Traditional farming--United States.; Whaling--New England.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Anecdotes.
Titles
Former title: Hanley collection, 1931-1937
Form/Genre
Audio-visual archives.; Correspondence.; Field recordings.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Manuscripts.; Photographic prints.; Sound recordings.; Transcripts.
Access
Listening and viewing access to the collection is unrestricted. The American Folklife Center is the custodial division for this collection; the original sound recordings are stored in the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division (hereafter M/B/RS), Library of Congress. Reference copies of sound recordings are available in analog and digitized forms (WAV and mp3 formats) through the Folklife Reading Room. Consult a reference librarian in the Folklife Reading Room for specific information.
An Access database contains entries for sound recordings and manuscripts that were digitized as part of the Save Our Sounds project. This database includes a short log for each recording, information on discs, interpolations of notes on disc sleeves, and background information on some of the recordings. This updated database is now available in the Folklife Reading Room.
Restrictions may apply concerning the use, duplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult a reference librarian in the Folklife Reading Room for specific information. To order audio reproductions, please refer to http://lcweb.loc.gov/rr/mopic/folkrec.html.
A selection of audio recordings from the American Dialect Society Collection is incorporated into the American Memory online presentation, "Voices from the Days of Slavery: Former Slaves Tell Their Stories" at http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/vfshtml/vfshome.html.
Acquisition
The American Dialect Society Collection (also referred to as the ADS Collection), includes disc recordings, typed transcriptions, and other documentation related to research for the Linguistic Atlas of New England, was donated to the Library of Congress on December 28, 1984, by the American Dialect Society. The collection originally included a number of duplicate discs, which were subsequently given to the Linguistic Archives at the University of Georgia, Athens. In cases where the original discs were missing from those donated to the Library, duplicated copies of those discs have been retained. In 1989 a tape comprising copies of some of the discs made by Frederic Cassidy, including seventeen recordings missing from the collection, were located among a separate collection of recordings loaned to the Library for duplication by the former president of the American Dialect Society, Raven I. McDavid. This tape has been added to the collection.
After the collection was donated to the Library in 1984, AFC reference librarian Gerald E. Parsons worked with linguists Katherine Langdon and Clare O'Leary to listen to each of the discs, provide a quality review, and prepare a database describing the content of each recording. In addition, the collection was arranged, described, and prepared for preservation duplication by Ross Gersten, Stephanie A. Hall, Francesca McLean, and John Vallier. In 2003-2004, Marcia K. Segal directed digitization work on the sound recordings, and finalized the collection guide. On July 7, 2000, the Save America's Treasures program jointly awarded the American Folklife Center (Library of Congress) and the Center for Folklife and Cultural Heritage (Smithsonian Institution) a $750,000 grant to save sound recordings and related materials (in other formats) in danger of being lost through physical deterioration. This program funded the Save Our Sounds project. The American Folklife Center selected several of its own collections for inclusion in the Save Our Sounds Project, including the American Dialect Society Collection. The digitization process was not exhaustive, due to the small quantity of materials in the collection. Only the audio disc recordings were digitized, because it was determined that ADS Collection recordings on the 10-inch preservation tape, formerly believed to be unique in the collection, existed in disc form (and thus an earlier generation) in the collection.
Collection Concordance by Format
Manuscript Materials
219 folders AFC MS001-218
Sound Recordings
(See also Appendix A)
891 audio discs (originals and copies) M/B/R/S AFS 24468-26016
1 10-inch reel tape (preservation) M/B/RS AFS 28438 (RWC 5793-94), AFS 25441 (RWC 5794)
1 10-inch reel tape (original) M/B/RS RWA 8547
78 10-inch reel tapes (preservation) M/B/RS AFS 24468-25767
74 7-inch reel tapes (reference) AFC AFS 24468-25767
1 audiocassette AFC SR01; Box 28
Electronic Media
1 zip disk AFC Box 1
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Administrative Files
    - Collection Guide, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Administrative, 1983-1993. (Folder 2)
      Deed of Gift and related manuscripts.
    - Administrative, 1979-1990, n.d. (Folder 3)
      Correspondence.
    - Contract Information. (Folder 4)
      Empty. See case file for related manuscripts.
    - Preliminary Inventory, 1983, n.d. (Folder 5)
      Field inventory and related manuscripts.
    - Research Aids, ca. 1987. (Folder 6)
      Related finding aids.
    - Reference Queries/Replies, 1985-1991. (Folder 7)
      After review by reference staff, the contents of this file, comprising correspondence to and from American Folklife Center reference staff, have been removed.
    - Contract Linguist's Lists, 1987, n.d. (Folder 8)
      Research manuscripts from Claire O'Leary.
    - Disc List, 1933, 1988, n.d. (Folder 9)
      Inventories of ADS Collection discs used by contract linguists. Includes lists of missing ADS Collection numbers (representing discs).
    - Inventory of Discs, n.d. (Folder 10)
      Original inventory of ADS Collection discs.
    - Log of Lists with AFS Numbers and Total Discs, ca. 1988. (Folder 11)
      Handwritten log of lists for groups of ADS Collection discs, and ADS Collection/AFS concordance.
    - Tape Logs, n.d. (Folder 12)
      Logs of audiotapes copied from ADS Collection discs.
    - Photographic Items, n.d. (Folder 13)
      Two photographs and one photocopy. See Series III (Graphic Images) for a description of the items.
    - Correspondence between Library of Congress and Fred G. Cassidy, 1984-1986. (Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: McDavid-Library of Congress, 1978-1984. (Folder 15)
      Correspondence from Raven McDavid to American Folklife Center staff; the majority of items date from 1984.
    - Correspondence: Metcalf-Library of Congress, 1983-1985. (Folder 16)
      Correspondence from Allan Metcalf to American Folklife Center staff.
    - Correspondence: Toombs-Library of Congress, 1983-1984. (Folder 17)
      Correspondence between Kenneth Toombs (University of South Carolina) and Joseph C. Hickerson.
    - Correspondence: Linguistic Atlas Project, 1990. (Folder 18)
      Correspondence between Ellen Johnson of the University of Georgia and Joseph C. Hickerson.
    - Correspondence: Informant Mailing, 1989. (Folder 19)
      Photocopies of undeliverable/returned envelopes sent to ADS Collection informants.
  - Project Correspondence
    Informants are anonymous in the following set of folders, but are identified with recording locations in the sections on phonetic transcriptions and narrative transcriptions. For Folders 20 through 35, see Appendix B for communities.
    - Delaware Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - District of Columbia Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 21)
    - Florida Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 22)
    - Georgia Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 23)
    - Kentucky Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 24)
    - Maryland Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 25)
    - New Jersey Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 26)
    - New York Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 27)
    - North Carolina Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 28)
    - Ohio Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 29)
    - Ontario, Canada, Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 30)
    - Pennsylvania Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 31)
    - South Carolina Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 32)
    - Virginia Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 33)
    - West Virginia Informants: Biographies and Community Information. (Folder 34)
    - Southern or Mid-Atlantic Informants: Community Information. (Folder 35)
  - Phonetic Transcriptions
    Locations listed below are the recording locations. See Boxes 18-23, Folders 69-199 for narrative transcriptions.
    - Hayes Transcription (Hiram H. Hayes; Granby, CT). (Box 3, Folder 36)
      (AFS 24490, 24492)
    - Palmer Transcription (Benjamin F. Palmer; Greenwich, CT). (Folder 37)
      (AFS 24705, 24708, 24711)
    - French Transcription (Battersen French; Walcott, CT). (Folder 38)
      (AFS 24751)
    - Bostwick Transcription (Leonard Bostwick; New Haven, CT). (Folder 39)
      (AFS 25073, 25074, 25077)
    - Fletcher Transcription (Lucy Rebecca Fletcher; Amherst, NH). (Folder 40)
      (AFS 25169, 25171, 25173)
    - Alley Transcription (Joshua Alden Alley; Jonesport, ME). (Folder 41)
      (AFS 25224, 25226, 25228, and 25230)
    - Gibbs Transcription (James H. Gibbs; Nantucket, MA). (Folder 42)
      (AFS 25555, 25557)
    - Dowse Transcription (Charles H. Dowse; Sherborn, MA). (Folder 43)
      (AFS 25597, 25599)
    - Pronunciations: ADS Collection Disc #1265. (Folder 44)
      Manuscripts of vowels and consonants spoken by Bernard Bloch, as written with unmodified symbols in the alphabet for the Linguistic Atlas of New England.
    - ADS Collection Disc #1075. (Folder 45)
      1 sheet of notes and a fragment of a whaling song text, sung by B.H. Gibbs
    - ADS Collection Disc #880. (Folder 46)
      Empty.
    - ADS Collection Disc #1040. (Folder 47)
      Notes.
    - ADS Collection Disc #14. (Folder 48)
      1 sheet of notes, and 4 sheets of a partial transcription
    - ADS Collection Discs #56 - 58 (George Green; Hartford, CT). (Folder 49)
      (AFS 24516-24518)
    - ADS Collection Discs #61 - 63 (C.T. Scott; Boston, MA). (Folder 50)
      (AFS 24520 - 24522)
    - ADS Collection Discs #65 - 67 (Annie Woodfin; Marblehead, MA). (Folder 51)
      (AFS 24526 - 24528)
    - ADS Collection Disc #70 (Jack Hanson; Marblehead, MA). (Folder 52)
      (AFS 24531)
    - ADS Collection Discs #74 - 75 (Eddie Bates; Cohasset, MA). (Folder 53)
      (AFS 24537, 24539)
    - ADS Collection Disc #79 (Mrs. Warren; Weston, MA). (Folder 54)
      (AFS 24543)
    - ADS Collection Discs #124 - 125 (Lyman Pearson; Byfield, MA). (Folder 55)
      (AFS 24584, 24586)
    - ADS Collection Discs #164 - 165 (Sam Nickerson; Eastham, MA). (Folder 56)
      (AFS 24652, 24654)
    - ADS Collection Disc #240 (John G. Murphy; Dorchester, MA). (Folder 57)
      (1 sheet referring to AFS 24759)
    - ADS Collection Disc #320 (Folder 58)
  - Original Disc Sleeves
    - ADS Collection Discs #1 - 120. (Box 4)
    - ADS Collection Discs #121 - 217. (Box 5)
    - ADS Collection Discs #218 - 327. (Box 6)
    - ADS Collection Discs #328 - 448. (Box 7)
    - ADS Collection Discs #449 - 587. (Box 8)
    - ADS Collection Discs #588 - 768. (Box 9)
    - ADS Collection Discs #769 - 851. (Box 10)
    - ADS Collection Discs #852 - 973. (Box 11)
    - ADS Collection Discs #974 - 1079 (missing: #1080). (Box 12)
    - ADS Collection Discs #1081 - 1279. (Box 13)
    - ADS Collection Discs #1280 - 1359. (Box 14)
    - ADS Collection Discs #1360 - 1412. (Box 15)
  - Photocopies of Disc Sleeves (Box 16)
    - AFS 24468 - 24643 (ADS Collection Discs #1 - 157). (Folder 59)
    - AFS 24644 - 24806 (ADS Collection Discs #159 - 281). (Folder 60)
    - AFS 24807 - 24962 (ADS Collection Discs #282 - 448). (Folder 61)
    - AFS 24963 - 25115 (ADS Collection Discs #449 - 704; no disc or sleeve for 705). (Folder 62)
    - AFS 25116 - 25271 (ADS Collection Discs #706 - 805). (Folder 63)
    - AFS 25272 - 25433 (ADS Collection Discs #806 - 931). (Folder 64)
    - AFS 25434 - 25556 (ADS Collection Discs #932 - 1069). (Folder 65)
    - AFS 25557 - 25641 (ADS Collection Discs #1070 - 1269). (Folder 66)
    - AFS 25642 - 25742 (ADS Collection Discs #1270 - 1379). (Box 17, Folder 67)
    - AFS 25743 - 26016 (ADS Collection Discs #1380 - 1412; I - XI; sleeves marked with Roman numerals lack ADS Collection original numbers.) (Folder 68)
  - Narrative Transcriptions
    The transcriptions are typewritten, with handwritten corrections and notations.
    - Alexander, Melvin L. (Box 18, Folder 69)
      (Hartford, CT; AFS 24845)
    - Alley, Captain [Captain Joshua Alley]. (Folder 70)
      (Jonesport, ME; AFS 25224, 25226, 25228, 25230)
    - Alley, J. [Captain Joshua Alley], 1-23. (Folder 71)
      (Jonesport, ME; AFS 25679-25701)
    - Alley, J. [Captain Joshua Alley], 24-44. (Folder 72)
      (Jonesport, ME; AFS 25702-25721)
    - Aydelotte, C. [Charles and Mrs. Charles Aydelotte]. (Folder 73)
      (Truro, MA: AFS 24644, 24648, 24650)
    - Baker, B. [Bessie Baker]. (Folder 74)
      (Beverly, MA; AFS 24562, 24564)
    - Bedell, L.B. [Lee B. Bedell]. (Folder 75)
      (Woodstock, New Brunswick, Canada; AFS 25274, 25276)
    - Belknap, L. [Leverett Belknap]. (Folder 76)
      (West Hartford, CT; AFS 24826, 24828, 24830, 24832)
    - Bemis, Dr. A.A. (Folder 77)
      (Spencer, MA; AFS 24797)
    - Blanchard, Mr. (Folder 78)
      (Yarmouth, ME; AFS 25184, 25185)
    - Boardman, Mrs. Anna. (Folder 79)
      (Northfield, VT; AFS 25545, 25547, 25549)
    - Carlton, E.B. (Folder 80)
      (Conway, NH; AFS 25337)
    - Carr, Mrs. E. [Emily Carr]. (Folder 81)
      (Newton, MA; AFS 24672)
    - Clark, H. [Henry Clark]. (Folder 82)
      (Old Saybrook, CT; AFS 24982)
    - Coe, O. [Olive Coe]. (Folder 83)
      (Litchfield, CT; AFS 25025, 25027, 25028, 25029, 25032
    - Coffin, Mr. (Folder 84)
      (Nantucket, MA; AFS 25,578)